A Guide to the Patteson Family Papers, 1734-1906
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Papers, 1734-1906
Library of Virginia
24295
4.15 cubic feet
Patteson Family
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Deposited by George W. Patteson, 3 March 1955.
Biographical/Historical Information
The Patteson family was prominent in Buckingham County, Virginia, and in Nelson County, Virginia during the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries. Both branches of the family descended from Thomas Patteson (ca. 1700-1745) of Albemarle County, Virginia.
Son Thomas Patteson (1734-1790) lived in Buckingham County. His son, David Patteson (1758-1846) became a prominent planter in the county and served as a major in the militia. David Patteson and his wife Judith (1761-1844) had twelve children, including David W. Patteson (1793-1851) who moved to Staunton, Virginia, and served in the Virginia House of Delegates, and James M. Patteson (1801-1862) who remained in Buckingham County and followed in his father's footsteps as a planter and militia major.
James M. Patteson and his wife Willie Ann Tompkins Patteson (b. 1817) had seven children, including George W. Patteson (1846-1926). Another son of Thomas Patteson, David Patteson (d. 1802) lived in what became Amherst, then Nelson County, Virginia. His son David R. Patteson (1810-1862) became a physician. David R. Patteson's son David Patteson (1810-1862) also became a doctor. He married Elizabeth Camm (b. 1815) and they had twelve children including Camm Patteson (1840-1909) and Sergeant S. Prentis Patteson (1856-1930) both of whom became lawyers in Albemarle County and Bedford County respectively. Their sister, Kate Patteson (b. 1855) married George W. Patteson of Buckingham County thereby reuniting the branches of the Patteson family.
Scope and Content Information
Papers, 1743-1906 (bulk 1820-1889), of the Patteson family of Buckingham County, Virginia, consisting of account books, accounts, agreements, Bible records, bonds, broadsides, correspondence, deeds, envelopes, estate records, genealogical notes, insurance policies, judicial records, memorandums, military commissions, minute books, passports, plats, powers of attorney, promissory notes, receipt books, receipts, reports, scrapbooks, surveys, tax records, and wills. Topics covered are the family histories of the David Patteson family of Buckingham County and the David Patteson family of Amherst County, Virginia; history of Buckingham and Amherst Counties; education of the Patteson children; Patteson family business interests; African Americans and slavery; Virginia politics and government; Patteson property in Mississippi; Buckingham County militia; the Civil War; railroads; overseers of the poor; and other matters.
Organization
Organized into the following six series:
I. Patteson Family Papers, 1743-1906.
II. Dr. David Patteson Family Papers, 1766 and 1830-1884.
III. Dibrell Estate Papers, 1799-1834.
IV. Charles Carter Estate Papers, 1821-1831.
V. Bible Records, Deeds, Wills, Commissions, Genealogical Notes.
VI. Account Books, Ledgers, etc., 1782-1893.
Contents List
- Papers, 1743-1906 (Box 1-5)
  Contains the papers of the Patteson family of Buckingham County, mainly David Patteson (1758-1846), James M. Patteson (1801-1862), and George W. Patteson (1846-1926) consisting of accounts, agreements, bonds, broadsides, correspondence, estate papers, judicial records, promissory notes, receipts, reports, surveys, tax records, and wills detailing the Pattesons' agricultural and business interests, including slaves, in Buckingham County and in Mississippi; and family matters. Of interest are letters from David W. Patteson of Staunton, Virginia, to James M. Patteson concerning Virginia politics during the 1830s and 1840s; letters from R. L. Patteson of Culpeper County, Virginia, to James M. Patteson concerning the early days of the Civil War; papers concerning James M. Patteson's Mississippi interests; an 1840 campaign biography of William Henry Harrison; and an 1831 arrest warrant for Peter Francisco for indebtedness.
  - Correspondence, 1743, 1780, 1795 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1805, 1806, 1808 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1810 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letters, receipts, etc., 1813-1816, 1818 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Invoices, receipts, etc., 1820-1821 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letters, receipts, powers of attorney, 1822 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Account, receipts, 1823 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Accounts, receipts, 1824 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Accounts, receipts, 1825 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Letters, accounts, receipts, etc., 1826 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Accounts, receipts, etc., 1827 (also see oversize) (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Accounts, receipts, etc., 1828 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Letters, accounts, receipts, etc., 1829 (also see oversize) (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Letters, accounts, receipts, etc., January-July 1830 (also see oversize) (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Letters, accounts, receipts, August-December 1830 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Bonds, Accounts, receipts, 1831 (also see oversize) (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Letters, accounts, receipts, etc., January-June 1831 (also see oversize) (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Letters, accounts, receipts, etc., July-December 1831 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Accounts, receipts, 1832 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Accounts, receipts, etc., January-July 1832 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Accounts, receipts, etc., August-December 1832 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Letters, accounts, receipts, etc., 1833 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Letters, accounts, receipts, January-May 1834 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Letters, accounts, receipts, etc., June-December 1834 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Accounts, receipts, etc., January-May 1835 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Accounts, receipts, June-December 1835 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Letters, accounts, receipts, etc., January-June 1836 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Letters, accounts, receipts, etc., July-December 1836 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Accounts, receipts, etc., 1837 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Letters, accounts, receipts, 1838 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Letters, accounts, receipts, 1839 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Letters, accounts, receipts, etc., 1840 - printed biography of William Henry Harrison (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Accounts, estate papers, receipts, etc., 1841 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Letters, accounts, receipts, etc., 1842 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Letters, accounts, receipts, etc., 1843 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Letters, receipts, etc., 1844 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Letters, accounts, receipts, etc., 1845 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Letters, accounts, receipts, etc., 1846 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Letters, accounts, receipts, etc., 1847 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Letters, Accounts, receipts, etc., 1848 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Letters, accounts, receipts, etc., 1849 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Letters, accounts, receipts, January-May 1850 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Letters, receipts, June-December 1850 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Letters, accounts, receipts, etc., 1851 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Letters, accounts, receipts, etc., 1852 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Letters, accounts, receipts, etc., 1853 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Letters, accounts, receipts, January-April 1854 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Accounts, receipts, etc., May-December 1854 (also see oversize) (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Letters, accounts, receipts, January-July 1855 (also see oversize) (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Letters, accounts, receipts, etc., August-December 1855 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Letters, accounts, receipts, etc., January-June 1856 (also see oversize) (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Letters, accounts, insurance, receipts, etc., July-December 1856 (also see oversize) (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Letters, accounts, receipts, etc., January-May 1857 (also see oversize) (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Letters, accounts, receipts, etc., June-December 1857 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Letters, accounts, receipts, etc., January-May 1858 (also see oversize) (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Letters, accounts, receipts, etc., June-December 1858 (also see oversize) (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Letters, accounts, receipts, etc., January-May 1859 (also see oversize) (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Letters, accounts, receipts, etc., June-December 1859 (also see oversize) (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Letters, accounts, receipts, etc., January-May 1860 (also see oversize) (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Letters, accounts, receipts, etc., June-December 1860 (also see oversize) (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Letters, accounts, receipts, etc., January-April 1861 (also see oversize) (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Letters, accounts, receipts, etc., May-December 1861 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Letters, accounts, receipts, etc., January-April 1862 (also see oversize) (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Letters, accounts, receipts, etc., May-December 1862 (also see oversize) (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Letters, accounts, receipts, etc., 1863 (also see oversize) (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Accounts, receipts, etc., January-May 1864 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Accounts, receipts, etc., June-December 1864 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Accounts, receipts, etc., 1865 (also see oversize) (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Accounts, receipts, etc., 1866 (also see oversize) (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Accounts, receipts, etc., January-March 1867 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Accounts, receipts, etc., April-December 1867 (also see oversize) (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Letters, accounts, receipts, etc., January-June 1868 (also see oversize) (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Accounts, receipts, etc., June-December 1868 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Accounts, receipts, etc., January-August 1869 (also see oversize) (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Accounts, receipts, etc., September-December 1869 (also see oversize) (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Accounts, receipts, etc., 1870 (also see oversize) (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Accounts, receipts, etc., 1871 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Accounts, receipts, etc., January-May 1872 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Accounts, receipts, etc., June-December 1872 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Accounts, receipts, etc., January-April 1873 (also see oversize) (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Accounts, receipts, etc., May-December 1873 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Accounts, receipts, etc., 1874 (also see oversize) (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Accounts, receipts, etc., 1875 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Accounts, receipts, etc., 1876 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Accounts, receipts, etc., 1877 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Accounts, receipts, etc., 1878 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Accounts, receipts, etc., 1879 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Accounts, receipts, etc., January-April 1880 (also see oversize) (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Accounts, receipts, etc., May-December 1880 (also see oversize) (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Accounts, receipts, etc., 1881 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Accounts, receipts, etc., January-July 1882 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Accounts, receipts, etc., August-December 1882 (also see oversize) (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Accounts, receipts, etc., January-June 1883 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Accounts, receipts, etc., July-December 1883 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Accounts, receipts, etc., 1884 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Accounts, receipts, etc., 1885 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Accounts, receipts, etc., 1886-1889 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Accounts, receipts, etc., 1890-1891 (also see oversize) (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Accounts, receipts, etc., 1894-1896 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Accounts, receipts, etc., 1906 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Undated letters (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Undated materials (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Undated covers (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Undated materials (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Undated materials (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Undated materials (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Undated materials (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Undated printed materials (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Undated medical remedies (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Undated recipes (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Undated materials (Box 5, Folder 12)
- David Patteson Family Papers, 1766, 1830-1884 (Box 5)
  Consists of the papers of the David Patteson family of Amherst, Bedford, and Nelson Counties, Virginia, mainly of David Patteson (1793-1862), Reuben Blakey Patteson (1834-1862), Camm Patteson (1840-1909), D. R. Patteson (1842-1861), Elizabeth Camm Patteson (b. 1815), and S. S. P. Patteson (1856-1930) of Bedford County and concerning family matters; business and agricultural concerns, including slaves; education of Reuben B. Patteson and Camm Patteson; family genealogical notes; and other matters. Of interest is a memorial concerning John Hampden Pleasants, editor of the Richmond Whig.
  - 24 July 1766 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - 1830-1837 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - 1842-1849 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - 1853-1858 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - 1859 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - 1860-1865 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - 1871-1878 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - 1880-1884 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Undated (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Genealogical chart (Box 5, Folder 22)
- Dibrell Estate Papers, 1799-1834 (Box 5)
  Contains the estate papers of Anthony Dibrell (d. 1816) of Buckingham County including accounts, receipts, correspondence, and judicial records regarding the estate.
  - 1799-1823 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - 1824-1825 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - 1826 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - 1827 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - 1828 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - 1829 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - 1830-1834 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Undated (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Account book-Dibrell estate (Box 5, Folder 31)
- Charles Carter Estate Papers, 1821-1831 (Box 6)
  Details the administration of the estate of Dr. Charles Carter (d. 1825) of Lancaster County, Virginia, by Joseph C. Cabell, and contains accounts, receipts, and correspondence concerning the estate.
  - Narrative (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - 1821-June 1822 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - July 1822-August 1823 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - September-December 1823 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - January-May 1824 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - July-December 1824 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - 1825 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - 1826 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - January-June 1827 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - July-December 1827 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - 1828-June 1830 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - July 1830-1831 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Undated (Box 6, Folder 13)
- Bible Records, Deeds, Plats, Wills, Commissions, and Genealogical Notes (Box 6)
  Contains Bible records, deeds, plats, wills, commissions, and genealogical notes of both the Patteson family of Buckingham County and the Patteson family of Nelson County.
  - Bible records (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Deeds (also see oversize) (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Plats (also see oversize) (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Wills (also see oversize) (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Commissions (also see oversize) (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Genealogical notes (Box 6, Folder 19)
- Account Books, Ledgers, etc., 1782-1893 (Box 7-8)
  Contains account books, receipt books, ledgers, scrapbooks, and minute books of both branches of the Patteson family. Of interest are the farm account book and store account book of David Patteson of Buckingham County; a saw mill account book; a passport doubling as a scrapbook; and the scrapbook of S. S. P. Patteson of Bedford County and Richmond, Virginia.
  - Farm account book and store account book, 1782-1818 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Account book, 1829, 1837 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Account book, 1832-1852 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Account book, 1833-1840 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Account book, 1838-1841 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Account index (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - James M. Patteson, 1820 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Receipt book, James M. Patteson, 1829-1832 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Receipt book, James M. Patteson, 1836-1844 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Bible fragment (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Saw mill account book (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Passport (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Farm account book, 1850-1868 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Inventory and account book, 1847 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - General store ledger, 1847-1868 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Scrapbook, 1861-1893 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Club minute book, 1878-1879 (Box 8, Folder 5)
- Oversize materials., Extent: 2 boxes. (Box 9-10)
  These are oversized items pulled from the first eight boxes of the collection. Placeholder tabs for these items are filed within the first eight boxes.
  - Accounts, 1829-1831 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Accounts, 1854-1859 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Accounts, 1860-1869 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Accounts, 1870-1874, 1880, 1882 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Will of Thomas Patteson, 25 December 1745 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Deeds, 1798 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Photostats of items located elsewhere in collection (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Broadside for land sale, 4 December 1827 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - List of delinquencies in the land tax, 1831 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Form, tax in kind, 13 January 1865 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Louisiana state lottery, 11 March 1890 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Account of sale of Robert R. Turner's property, 2 September 1845 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Deeds and land grants, 1787-1859 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Plat, 27 April 1807 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Commission from Thomas Jefferson to Thomas A. Patterson[sic], 22 February 1809 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - The Alliance Exchange, 14 February 1891 (Box 10, Folder 5)